<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>books on Kablamo</title>
    <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/categories/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in books on Kablamo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.kablamo.org/categories/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Multipliers</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/multipliers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/multipliers/</guid>
      <description>Some leaders are Multipliers and some are Diminishers. Multipliers make everyone around them smarter and more productive. Diminishers do the opposite. This book teaches people how to be Multipliers by describing the 5 disciplines (behaviors) of Multipliers.
  Multipliers on the web  YouTube:  Introduction to Multipliers - 4 minutes - Liz Wiseman speaking at a business conference The Push/Pull of Leadership - 3 minutes - Liz Wiseman speak to Standford eCorner - &amp;hellip; a story that illustrates how great leaders help their employees overcome struggles, while also remembering to step away and hand back responsibility to give them a chance to grow and gain confidence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Formula</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/the-formula/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/the-formula/</guid>
      <description>How to be a successful &#34;master parent&#34;:  Have a vision. Master parents implement this intentionally and strategically. They are not passive. Make time to learn about parenting &amp;ndash; often by reading. Adapt to the child. Master parents study the child closely and tailor their approach. Define a few strict rules but let the child make the remaining decisions. Perform 8 key roles for kids:  The early learning partner The flight engineer The fixer The revealer The philosopher The model The negotiator The GPS      The story behind the book &amp;ldquo;The Formula&amp;rdquo; is a collaboration between a Boston Globe reporter and a Harvard professor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 Things Mentally Strong Parents Don&#39;t Do</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/mentally-strong-parents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/mentally-strong-parents/</guid>
      <description>This book is a list of 13 bad parenting behaviors and what you can do about each behavior as a parent. I like that its totally practical and you can immediately run out and start applying Amy Morin&#39;s advice. By the way, I see plenty of my own flaws listed in the 13 bad kid behaviors. Thats a little uncomfortable.
The author is a therapist who specializes in children.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Secrets of Happy Families</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/the-secrets-of-happy-families/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/the-secrets-of-happy-families/</guid>
      <description>The Secrets of Happy Families
Agile families
 Just like agile software development: iterative  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>