<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: experiments | KABLAMO]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.kablamo.org/categories/experiments/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.kablamo.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-25T22:41:57-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.kablamo.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Johnson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kablamo@kablamo.org]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An experiment - living with less than 200 things]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.kablamo.org/2014/03/24/experiments/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.kablamo.org/2014/03/24/experiments</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><strong>Stuff is expensive to buy.</strong>  Especially when I end up only using things
once or twice like books, dvds, dress shoes, and ties.</li>
<li><strong>Stuff is expensive to store.</strong>  One time I had to rent a storage locker
because I couldn&rsquo;t take my things when I moved to China.  Some people get
big houses with walk in closets and a three car garage.</li>
<li><strong>Stuff is expensive to maintain.</strong>  Broken stuff needs to be fixed.  Owning
a house means I need to fix the roof. Owning a car means I need to change
the tires.</li>
<li><strong>Stuff is time consuming to maintain.</strong>  I have to dust my stuff.
A bigger house means more sweeping.
A bigger yard means more mowing. Owning a car means cleaning it and
changing the oil and scraping ice off the windows.<br/>
I need to go to the store to find replacement parts,
batteries, light bulbs, cleaning supplies, and duct tape.</li>
<li><strong>Stuff is stressful to own.</strong>  I might
lose it or dent it or scratch it or drop it or step on it.  Or it might
catch on fire.  Or someone might steal it.  Sometimes I get so stressed I buy
insurance for my stuff.</li>
<li><strong>Stuff reduces my freedom.</strong>  Its hard to move to new place because I have
to carry all my stuff with me.</li>
</ul>


<p>Therefore I have decided to live with less stuff.  So I hereby declare war on
my stuff.  And also on my things.  Here is my 4 point plan to free myself from
the tedious tyranny of too many things:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Point 1:</strong> Keep a comprehensive inventory of all my stuff.</li>
<li><strong>Point 2:</strong> Ruthlessly reduce the number of things in my inventory to less than 200.</li>
<li><strong>Point 3:</strong> No new stuff unless I throw out some old stuff first.</li>
<li><strong>Point 4:</strong> Have a beer.</li>
</ul>


<p>If I were hard core I would throw out everything I didn&rsquo;t use in the last 6
months.  Maybe I&rsquo;ll be hard core at some point in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An experiment - No dessert forever]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.kablamo.org/2014/01/01/no-dessert-forever/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.kablamo.org/2014/01/01/no-dessert-forever</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For years I have been hearing people say sugar is the new bad thing.  So I
finally got around to reading up on this claim.  Here is what I learned.</p>

<h1>Nutrition</h1>

<p>Food is composed of <strong>carbohydrates, fats, proteins, water, vitamins,</strong> and
<strong>minerals</strong>.  Of course, I sometimes swallow stuff that is not on that list
but the list is comprehensive in the sense that it covers everything my body
needs.  Notice that sugar is not in the list.  My body breaks down carbs and
fats into glucose (sugar) which can be used by my body as energy.</p>

<p>This means sugar has <em>zero</em> nutritional value.  There is no reason to ever
eat any.  Humans do not require sugar.</p>

<p>I have always been smug about the fact that I don&rsquo;t throw away my money on a
caffeine addiction.  But suddenly I realize I have been foolishly spending my
money on sugar.</p>

<h1>No dessert forever</h1>

<p>As part of my long term plan to someday somehow acquire a svelte physique, I
hereby <strong>reject and repudiate</strong> the harmful cultural ritual known as dessert.
The rules are:</p>

<ul>
<li>No dessert forever.  No ice cream, no cake, no pie.</li>
<li>No candy forever.  No free candy or chocolate from the nice people at the office.</li>
<li>No fruit juice forever.</li>
<li>Exceptions

<ul>
<li>85%+ dark chocolate</li>
<li>Honey</li>
<li>Fruit</li>
<li>Small quantities of desserts that I have never had before.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Sources:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Food_energy">Wikipedia: Food energy</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2235907/">Evidence for sugar addiction</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.health.harvard.edu/newsletters/Harvard_Heart_Letter/2011/September/abundance-of-fructose-not-good-for-the-liver-heart">Abundance of fructose not good for the liver, heart</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nickwinter.net/experiments">Nick Winter</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
