<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>financial-independence on Kablamo</title>
    <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/categories/financial-independence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in financial-independence on Kablamo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.kablamo.org/categories/financial-independence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>But I want to spend down my nest egg to zero</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/but-i-want-to-spend-down-my-nest-egg-to-zero/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/but-i-want-to-spend-down-my-nest-egg-to-zero/</guid>
      <description>photo by woodleywonderworks
 The problem with this is you can&amp;rsquo;t predict when you will die. On average, Americans live until about 80. But thats the average. Half of everyone will live longer than that. What will you do if you live to age 100?
Despite this, lots of retirement calculators and planning manuals tell you to enter in your age of death. But you can&amp;rsquo;t predict this. So don&amp;rsquo;t do your retirement planning like you can.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Withdrawal rates</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/withdrawal-rates/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/withdrawal-rates/</guid>
      <description>Lets say you reach your goal of retirement. You quit your job sit on your sailboat and eat pineapples all day. The wind is in your hair, you are relaxed and carefree, and you have pineapple breath. All because you have a formidable nest egg and can live comfortably off your investment earnings.
But how do you know how much of your nest egg you can withdraw and spend each year?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The best personal finance blogs</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/the-best-personal-finance-blogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/the-best-personal-finance-blogs/</guid>
      <description>Here is a short list of the very best personal finance blogs on the internet. All of these websites are constructed entirely of Excellence. They are so good I read every post in their archives. Each author has found a way to retire in under 10 years with fairly normal human level salaries and has insightful things to say about getting to financial freedom.
Mr Money Mustache If I was marooned on a deserted island &amp;hellip; with limited bandwidth and could only read one blog, this is the one I would choose.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The math behind the calculator</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/math-behind-the-calculator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/math-behind-the-calculator/</guid>
      <description>Networthify.com calculates how many years you have to retirement. Lots of people have been curious about how it arrives at the magic number. The answer to this question is: Math!
More specifically the equation which drives the calculator is derived from two common formulas used for dealing with compound interest. Many people must have done this before me but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find an example online and I enjoyed doing the math anyway.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spending money shortens your life</title>
      <link>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/spending-shortens-your-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kablamo.org/articles/spending-shortens-your-life/</guid>
      <description>Photo by Thomas Hawk
 One morning you awake to find the tooth fairy made an accounting error in your favor. She left $15 million under your pillow. Now you have some choices to make. Here is one: Would you continue to wake up each day and go to your current job?
We all have a certain amount of time to live. Every dollar we earn is given in exchange for time spent working.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>